Draper Corporation Glass Plate Negatives 6612 GPN
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series A: 5 x 7 inch negatives.
  - Draper Co. loom, Model E, with duflex (?) harness (Box 7, Folder 27)
    Negative no.A27. 1894-1900. Image depicts a Draper Company Model E loom with a duplex harness. The loom has been photographed against a temporary background set up within an unknown mill. According to a 1900 catalog published by Draper, the E model loom had a regular pattern for prints and sheetings. The Draper Company, located in Hopedale, Massachusetts, manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Negative 22, in this box, for a close-up view of the battery on this loom. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 2, Item 27 for print of this negative.
  - Loom: D Model LH, Draper Company, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    Negative no.A31. Image depicts a view of a Draper Company D Model LH Loom, photographed against a sheet, most likely within an unknown mill. This model appears very similar to the D Model loom seen in Box 9, Negative 73, but is not exactly the same. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Draper Loom - D Model LH Mar 1898." The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 2, Item 31 for print of this negative.
  - Loom: A Model, Draper Company (Box 7, Folder 37)
    Negative no.A37. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a Draper Company A Model loom, photographed against a sheet, most likely within an unknown mill. The loom has a battery on the right-hand side. The Model A loom was also called the 1894 pattern, and was obsolete by 1900. The Model A loom had a shorter lay and shuttle box than was used by Draper by 1900, had a Mason take-up and plain rocker motions. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 2, Item 37 for print of this negative.
  - Loom: D Model (rear view), Draper Company, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    Negative no.A38. 1898? Image depicts the rear view of a D-model loom set up on a white cloth on the floor, with a curtain draped behind it for photography purposes, most likely within an unknown mill. The D-model loom was considered a heavy standard loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Box 9, Negative 73 for the front view of this loom, which was dated from 1898. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 2, Item 38 for print of this negative.
  - Draper Company Loom - E Model, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    Negative no.A39. Image depicts a view of an E-model loom from 1900, set up on a white cloth on the floor, with a curtain draped behind it for photography purposes, most likely within an unknown mill. The loom has a battery on the right-hand side. Draper Company is incised on the frame. Very similar (if not identical) to the loom seen in Box 7, Negative 27. The E-model loom had a regular pattern for prints and sheetings. The Draper Company, located in Hopedale, Massachusetts, manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 2, Item 39 for print of this negative.
  - Drafting Room, October 1900, Draper Company (Box 8, Folder 44)
    Negative no.A44. October 1900. Image depicts a view of the Drafting Room at the Draper Company. Individual drafting tables on the right appear to be separated by sheets. The right side of the room appears to be flooded with light. Windows are visible in the rear. More drafting tables with cloth (?) spread out on them are in the foreground. The calendar on the rear wall reads October 1900. This view is a different angle from that seen in Box 1, Negative 999,Box 3, Negative 1040 and Negative 1051. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 44 for print of this negative.
  - Loom: E Model, Draper Company (Box 8, Folder 46)
    Negative no.A46. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of an E-model loom with one battery on the right side. "Hopedale Draper Company Massachusetts" incised on frame. The E model loom was for a regular pattern for prints and sheetings. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 46 for print of this negative.
  - Draper Company Loom frame (D Model), 1898 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    Negative no.A47. Image depicts a view of a D-model loom frame, seen here without any interior parts attached. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom frame (D Model) May 1898." The Draper Company, located in Hopedale, Massachusetts, manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 47 for print of this negative.
  - F Model Loom, Draper Company, 1900 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    Negative no.A48. Image depicts a view of an F-model loom seen here from the rear. The F model loom was designed for an extra heavy pattern for goods 72 inches and wider. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom - F Model Feb 15, 1900." See Negative 55, in this box, for a close-up view of an F model loom from the end showing the picker stick. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 48 for print of this negative.
  - Dobby Loom, D Model, Draper Company (Box 8, Folder 49)
    Negative no.A49. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a D-model dobby loom, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. The battery is on the right with a long box for the bobbins. A dobby loom is a loom equipped with a dobby and capable of weaving small figures. The dobby is a mechanism attached to a loom for controlling the operation of the harnesses. Dobbies are made so that they can operate up to 25 harnesses and by this means figured cloths can be woven. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 49 for print of this negative.
  - C Model Loom with a duplex harness, Draper Company (Box 8, Folder 50)
    Negative no.A50. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a C-model loom with a duplex harness, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. The battery is on the right-hand side, although there appears to be no box for the bobbins. The harness is the frame containing the heddles through which the warp threads are drawn prior to weaving. By lifting or lowering the harnesses in the loom the shed is formed. The shed is the opening formed when some warp threads are raised by their harnesses while others are left down. Forming the shed is the first action in weaving, and it is through the shed that the shuttle passes in inserting the filling. This loom contains two harnesses. The C model loom was Draper's first heavy pattern loom and was obsolete by 1900. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 50 for print of this negative.
  - B Model Loom, Draper Company (Box 8, Folder 52)
    Negative no.A52. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a B model loom, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. The B model loom, also called the 1895 loom, was the Draper standard for prints and other light goods until 1898. The loom was obsolete by 1900. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 52 for print of this negative.
  - D Model Loom with a worm gear take-up motion, Draper Company (Box 8, Folder 54)
    Negative no.A54. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a D model loom with a worm gear take-up motion, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. The take-up motion is a mechanism on a loom for taking up the cloth as it is woven. The speed with which it performs this action determines the number of picks per inch. A worm gear take-up motion is continuous, as opposed to the intermittent motion. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 54 for print of this negative.
  - Close-up view of F Model Loom, Draper Company, 1900 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    Negative no.A55. Image depicts a close-up view of an F-model loom seen from one end, showing the picker stick. (The picker stick, by delivering a sharp blow to the shuttle, causes the shuttle to be thrown from one shuttle box, across the race plate, into the opposite shuttle box.) The F model loom was designed for an extra heavy pattern for goods 72 inches and wider. A notation on the back of the print reads: "F Model Loom Feb 1900." See Negative 48, in this box, for a broader view of an F model loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 55 for print of this negative.
  - J Model, 20-Harness Dobby Loom, Draper Company (Box 9, Folder 62)
    Negative no.A62. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a J model dobby loom, with 20 harnesses. A dobby loom is a loom equipped with a dobby and capable of weaving small figures. The dobby is a mechanism attached to a loom for controlling the operation of the harnesses. Dobbies are made so that they can operate up to 25 harnesses and by this means figured cloths can be woven. The harness is the frame containing the heddles through which the warp threads are drawn prior to weaving. By lifting or lowering the harnesses in the loom the shed is formed. The shed is the opening formed when some warp threads are raised by their harnesses while others are left down. Forming the shed is the first action in weaving, and it is through the shed that the shuttle passes in inserting the filling. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 62 for print of this negative.
  - Dobby Loom (side view), Draper Company (Box 9, Folder 63)
    Negative no.A63. 1894-1900. Image depicts the side view of dobby loom by Draper Company. Possibly the side view of the dobby loom seen in Negative 62 and Negative 64, in this box, which is described as a 20-harness J Model, but it is difficult to establish from this angle. Clearly this loom has multiple harnesses on it. A dobby loom is a loom equipped with a dobby and capable of weaving small figures. The dobby is a mechanism attached to a loom for controlling the operation of the harnesses. Dobbies are made so that they can operate up to 25 harnesses and by this means figured cloths can be woven. The harness is the frame containing the heddles through which the warp threads are drawn prior to weaving. By lifting or lowering the harnesses in the loom the shed is formed. The shed is the opening formed when some warp threads are raised by their harnesses while others are left down. Forming the shed is the first action in weaving, and it is through the shed that the shuttle passes in inserting the filling. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 63 for print of this negative.
  - J Model, 20-Harness Dobby Loom (rear view), Draper Company (Box 9, Folder 64)
    Negative no.A64. 1894-1900. Image depicts the rear view of a J model dobby loom, with 20 harnesses, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. A dobby loom is a loom equipped with a dobby and capable of weaving small figures. The dobby is a mechanism attached to a loom for controlling the operation of the harnesses. Dobbies are made so that they can operate up to 25 harnesses and by this means figured cloths can be woven. The harness is the frame containing the heddles through which the warp threads are drawn prior to weaving. By lifting or lowering the harnesses in the loom the shed is formed. The shed is the opening formed when some warp threads are raised by their harnesses while others are left down. Forming the shed is the first action in weaving, and it is through the shed that the shuttle passes in inserting the filling. See Negative 62, in this box, for the front view of this loom and Negative 63, in this box, for what is probably the side view of this loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 64 for print of this negative.
  - Loom: A Model, side view, Draper Company, 1894 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    Negative no.A65. Image depicts the side view of an A Model loom by Draper Company. The A Model loom was the first loom sent out to various manufacturers by Draper; it had a shorter lay and shuttle box than later used, a Mason take-up, and plain rocker motions. By 1900 it was obsolete. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom - Pulley End A Model Dec 22, 1894." The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 65 for print of this negative.
  - Loom: A Model, side view showing battery, Draper Company, 1900 (Box 9, Folder 66)
    Negative no.A66. Image depicts the side view of an A Model loom by Draper Company, this side showing the battery. Photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. Note the short drop box beneath the battery. The A Model loom was the first loom sent out to various manufacturers by Draper; it had a shorter lay and shuttle box than later used, a Mason take-up, and plain rocker motions. By 1900 it was obsolete. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom - A Model Mpv 25, 1900." The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 66 for print of this negative.
  - B Model Loom, Draper Company (Box 9, Folder 67)
    Negative no.A67. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a B model loom, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. The B model loom, also called the 1895 loom, was the Draper standard for prints and other light goods until 1898. The loom was obsolete by 1900. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 67 for print of this negative.
  - Loom: D Model, Draper Company, 1898 (Box 9, Folder 73)
    Negative no.A73. Image depicts a D-model loom set up on a white cloth on the floor, with a curtain draped behind it for photography purposes, most likely within an unknown mill. Draper Company is incised on the top crosspiece. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom - D Model, Mar 22, 1898." The D-model loom was considered a heavy standard loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Box 7, Negative 38 for what is most likely the rear view of this loom. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 73 for print of this negative.
  - Loom (sent to Queen City Cotton Company, 1894), Draper Company (Box 9, Folder 74)
    Negative no.A74. Image depicts a loom with two batteries. The area has been set off with a sheet to isolate the loom for photography, most likely within an unknown mill. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom (first fair, sent to Queen City Cotton Co.), Dec. 22, 1894." The reference to a fair could be a reference to a textile machinery exposition of some sort. The Queen City Cotton Co. was located in Burlington, Vt. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 74 for print of this negative.
  - Loom: D Model, Northrup Loom, Draper Company, 1898 (Box 9, Folder 80)
    Negative no.A80. Image depicts a D-model Northrup loom set up against a white curtain draped behind it for photography purposes, most likely within an unknown mill. Draper Company is incised on the top crosspiece; "The Northrup Loom" is clearly visible on the front of the loom. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom - D Model, Mar, 1898." The D-model loom was considered a heavy standard loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and specifically Northrup looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 3, Item 80 for print of this negative.
  - Keene drawing-in frame, Draper Company (Box 10, Folder 87)
    Negative no.A87. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a Keene drawing-in frame manufactured by the Draper Company. Drawing-in is the process of entering the warp ends from the warp beam through the eyes of the correct heddles on the respective harnesses. The warp beam here is on the right; the warp ends are being drawn through the heddles but the angle of the photograph does not show that clearly, since the frame is seen from the side. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 4, Item 87 for print of this negative.
  - Close-up view of gears on Speeder, Draper Company (Box 10, Folder 89)
    Negative no.A89. 1894-1900]. Image depicts a close-up view of the gears on the end of a speeder, which is a term sometimes used for the third machine in a series of roving frames, or applied to roving frames in general. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Negative 94, in this box, for an expanded view of this machine. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 4, Item 89 for print of this negative.
  - Speeder (rear view), Draper Company (Box 10, Folder 90)
    Negative no.A90. 1891-1895. Image depicts the view from the rear of a speeder, which is a term sometimes used for the third machine in a series of roving frames, or applied to roving frames in general. See Negative 94, in this box, for the front view of this machine. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 4, Item 90 for print of this negative.
  - Speeder, Draper Co. (Box 10, Folder 94)
    Negative no.A94. 1891-1895. Image depicts a speeder, which is a term sometimes used for the third machine in a series of roving frames, or applied to roving frames in general. "Draper Company Hopedale Massachusetts" can be seen on the side of the machine. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Negative 90, in this box, for the rear view of this machine. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 1, Folder 4, Item 94 for print of this negative.
  - Prospect Heights, units 7-14, Milford, Massachusetts (Box 11, Folder 119)
    Negative no.A119. 1901-1916? Image depicts a view of units 7 through 14 at Prospect Heights in Milford, Massachusetts The units are connected townhouse style, with eight separate entrances, and are made out of brick. The entire building is two stories with a small window visible in the third story on each end. There are chimneys on each end, in the middle, and two in the rear. Grass plots line the front, separated by walkways to each entrance. A large grassy area is in the foreground. Freestanding clotheslines are visible in the background at each end. These units were built for Draper Company employees and are believed to have been designed by Peabody & Stearns. See Box 23, Negative 346 for what appears to be another view of this same housing. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 2, Folder 1, Item 119 for print of this negative.
  - Twister, G Model, Draper Company (Box 13, Folder 143)
    Negative no.A143. 1901-1916. Image depicts a view of a G Model twister manufactured by the Draper Company. The twister is photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill, and is seen from the side rather than head-on. "Draper Company" is embossed on the piece on the floor, leaning against the machine. A twister is a machine for twisting together two or more separate ends, making either a ply yarn or a cable yarn, or for inserting additional twist in a single end. It is made with either a pin creel or beam creel; in this case, a pin creel, which can be seen on the top of the twister. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 2, Folder 2, Item 143 for print of this negative.
  - Houses on Bancroft Parkway (Box 13, Folder 152)
    Negative no.A152. 1901-1916. Image depicts a view of Bancroft Parkway in Hopedale, Massachusetts Substantial two-story, wood- shingled houses line the unpaved road. Electric poles can be seen on the left-hand side of the road. Most of the houses have two chimneys and are duplexes, as Hopedale housing built for Draper Company employees was generally not larger than a duplex. See Negative 157, in this box, and Box 14, Negative 163 for other views of these houses. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 2, Folder 2, Item 152 for print of this negative.
  - Close-up view of house on Bancroft Parkway (Box 13, Folder 153)
    Negative no.A153. 1901-1916. Image depicts a closer view of a house on Bancroft Parkway, done in the Dutch Colonial (or gambrel) style. The house is wood-shingled, has shutters on every window, and has two separate entrances in the front; it is most likely a duplex. (See Box 14, Negative 171 for another view of this house, although lacking the bushes in the front yard.) A similar wood-shingled house can be glimpsed behind this one in the left background. These houses were built for Draper Company employees. See Box 14, Negative 172 and Negative 175 for other views of houses on Bancroft Parkway, and Box 14, Negative 166 for a view of the back yards of the houses on Bancroft Parkway. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 2, Folder 2, Item 153 for print of this negative.
  - Two houses on Bancroft Parkway (Box 13, Folder 155)
    Negative no.A155. 1901-1916. Image depicts two houses on Bancroft Parkway. The house on the right is a substantial two-and-a- half story wood-shingled house, with two separate porches, most likely a duplex. The house to the left, which is somewhat hidden by trees, is a wood-shingled duplex with two entrances. (This house can also be seen in Box 14, Negative 169.) The unpaved road is wide and curves around between the two houses. Another house can be glimpsed on the left. These houses were built for Draper Company employees. See also Box 14, Negative 197. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 2, Folder 2, Item 155 for print of this negative.
  - Two houses at the junction of Bancroft Parkway (Box 13, Folder 156)
    Negative no.A156. 1901-1916. Image depicts two houses at the junction of Bancroft Parkway and an unknown street. The house in the center is a substantial two-and-a-half story wood-shingled house, with at least three chimneys. The house to the left of that is also wood-shingled, has at least three chimneys, and two separate entrances. Both are most likely duplexes. Electric poles run along the left side of the unpaved street. Bushes and woods appear to be at the corner of the street on the right. These houses were built for Draper Company employees. See also Negative 160, in this box. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 2, Folder 2, Item 156 for print of this negative.
  - Three different house styles on Bancroft Parkway (Box 13, Folder 157)
    Negative no.A157. 1901-1916. Image depicts three different house styles in houses on Bancroft Parkway. All are substantial wood-shingled houses with two separate entrances. The house in the center is two-and-a-half stories with two gables. The house to the right of that is also two-and-a-half stories with a steeply sloping back roof. The house on the far right is in the Dutch Colonial, or gambrel, style. All are duplexes. Part of another house can be glimpsed on the left. The foreground appears to be open ground. These houses were built for Draper Company employees. See also Negative 152, in this box, and Box 14, Negative 163 for other views of these houses. 5 x 7 in. See Collection 6612 P, Box 2, Folder 2, Item 157 for print of this negative.
  - Houses on Bancroft Parkway (Box 13, Folder 158)